<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A recitall of that which hath happened in the kings armie, since the taking of the suburbes of Paris, vntill the taking of the towne of Humflet.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B13970</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99891595</idno>
  <idno type="VID">190342</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240909444</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">STC 13139</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide C.132.h.25[15]</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99891595</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99891595e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B13970)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 190342)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; C20:1[15])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A recitall of that which hath happened in the kings armie, since the taking of the suburbes of Paris, vntill the taking of the towne of Humflet.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By T. Orwin] for Tobie Cooke,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1590.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>A translation from the original French.</note>
                  <note>With a blank first leaf? Title page is A2.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Original French title not traced.</note>
                  <note>Title page has armorial device; head-piece, initial.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">France --  History --  Wars of the Huguenots, 1562-1598 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:190342:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:190342:1"/>
            <p>A Recitall of that which hath happened in the <hi>Kings Armie, since the taking of</hi> the Suburbes of Paris, vntill <hi>the taking of the Towne of Humflet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Imprinted at London for <hi>Tobie Cooke.</hi> 1590.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:190342:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:190342:2"/>
            <head>A RECITALL OF that which happened in the Kings <hi>Armie, since the taking of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbes</hi> of Paris, vntill the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <hi>of the Towne of Phalesey.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough that common examples doo sufficiently shewe vs, that pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient forbearing sufficeth to giue legitimate Princes the infallible victorie of Rebellions, without the hazarding of battailes; yet not withstanding, the loue of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie hath been so great towards his subiects, that for to redeeme them from the oppressions which they suffer, and are yet to suffer through the continuance of a long warre, hee hath desired nothing more for the speedie ending thereof, (since the taking of armes in hand) than to aduenture the iustice of his cause, vpon the successe of a battaile, hauing sought to draw all his enemies thereunto by al meanes possible. First of all, when they sought him in Normandie, they reported, that they went not to giue battaile, but to a victorie alreadie gotten. At which time, (in their sight) he went to besiege and take the towne and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:190342:3"/>of <hi>Gamashe,</hi> and two dayes after to recouer the towne of <hi>Ewe;</hi> all their Armie beeing but 3. leagues off. Since that, in his returne, hee made fiue or sixe dayes iourney on their side of the <hi>Some:</hi> not passing the Riuer at <hi>Pont del arche,</hi> as hee might haue done, but deferred to passe at <hi>Muellan,</hi> for to receaue them if they would haue giuen him battaile. And since like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, after the taking of the Suburbs of <hi>Paris,</hi> the day of his departure thence, his Maiestie kept his Armie ranged in battaile foure howres, to see if there wold be anie effect of that furie, in which it was reported they were arriued at <hi>Paris:</hi> as it hath been more am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie declared in the former discourse. And his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie being at the village of <hi>Linars</hi> vnder <hi>Mountlhery,</hi> remained there a whole daye, thinking that his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, hauing been rested and refreshed three dayes in the towne of <hi>Paris,</hi> would haue gathered stomacke to haue come out, and haue giuen him battaile there; which if they had put in practise, the King would haue met them halfe way. But being aduertised, that in stead of troubling of themselues with this busines, they thought it lesse dangerous to shew their choler, in saccaging the particular inhabitants of the said ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; executing those themselues, whō al men thought they should haue defended from beeing executed by others: imputing to the richest sort, and such as were easiest to be trodden vnder foote, that they were the Kings friends (to colour thereby their massacre and pillaging from punishment) regarding neither quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie nor age, killing and drowning manie, both men and women; making the world beleeue, that that which was executed through the valor of the Kings
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:190342:3"/>Armie, was enterprised by practises and intelligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to excuse the slender care, and small courage of those, which were within the Citie: where they li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing at their pleasure, being so nested that there was no meanes to drawe them out, his Maiestie determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to take the towne and castle of <hi>Estampes,</hi> beeing mooued thereunto by the aduertisement hee had, that the Lord <hi>Cleremont</hi> of <hi>Lodesue</hi> with fiftie or three score Gentlemen had thrust themselues into it, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the assurance the Duke <hi>de Maine</hi> had giuen them, (and confirmed by manie of his letters which were intercepted) that he wold come to relieue them with all his Armie. His Maiestie knowing that the Duke <hi>de Maine</hi> had bound himselfe by his faith and honour to relieue <hi>Estampes,</hi> thought to giue him oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion to seeke the battaile, through the besiegeing of it: and in hope thereof departed from the village of <hi>Linars</hi> vpon Sunday the first day of Nouember, and arriued at <hi>Estampes</hi> with all his Armie; which he had inuironed the same day in the morning: &amp; although he could not come thether before day light was shut in, yet at his first comming he wonne the suburbes, which the enemies made showe they would defend. The very same night the town likewise was wonne, and the men of warre did retire themselues into the castle; which was immediately inuironed, &amp; appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches made, and two Culuerins were placed in batte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, the Tuesday folowing by faire day light. Which they within seeing, and that the Armie which should haue relieued them, did not appeare, nor that there was any newes of it, demanded a Parle, and yeelded themselues the same day, with condition that eight
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:190342:4"/>of them should remaine prisoners, vntill such time as they should cause seuen or eight others to be deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, who were named vnto them. His Maiestie after the said agreement, did shew that fauour to the Lord <hi>Cleremont</hi> of <hi>Lodesue,</hi> to two masters of the Camp, &amp; vnto fiue others that shuld haue remained prisoners, to send them away vppon their oathes: so that there departed out of the said Castle, about 40. Gentemen, and aboue 200. souldiers, who were safely conduct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed halfe way vnto <hi>Paris.</hi> His Maiestie considering that the poore towne of <hi>Estampes</hi> in foure moneths had been three times taken, and that although it had been necessarie for him to haue kept a good garrison in it, yet notwithstanding (of his own nature being as easie to be ouercome with pitie and clemencie, as hee is inuincible to his enemies) was content to take no other assurance of the towne, than the oathes of the inhabitants, wherein hee reposed his trust. And further, to put them out of doubt, that the castle shuld be no meane of their rigorous vsage hereafter, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to rase the said castle, &amp; to commit the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of the town to the townsmen only, perswading himself that they cōparing the vsage which they had had at his hands and his enemies together, it was the surest Garrison, to keepe them in obedience. His said Maiestie remained ther vntil the saturday folowing, during which time there arriued a Gentleman sent from the Queene Dowager, bringing a request, which she presented vnto his Maiestie for to beseech him, to shew her iustice for the cruell slaughter com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vpon the person of the late king her husband. His Maiestie deferred the aunswere of this request,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:190342:4"/>vntill such time as he sate in counsell; where beeing the daye following, the Gentleman was called for; who after hee had deliuered his message, the request was read alowd in the presence of al the Princes Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reshalls of <hi>France,</hi> and principall Lords and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, of which there was then a great number about King. By which request, besides the desiring of his Maiestie, she did adiure not onely the Princes &amp; No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie of <hi>France,</hi> but also all the Princes of Christen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to be assisters in this iust cause. His Maiestie making aunswere himselfe, declared that he highlie commended her vehemencie in following this sute, and sent his said request vnto his Court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment transported to <hi>Towers,</hi> that his Atturney gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, with the Atturuey of the said Ladie, might make the information against the offenders, to the intent the matter might bee determined afterward in his presence, in manner and forme conuenient. And for his owne part, although the said sute were commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable in the said Ladie, yet he wold not cease to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secute the matter, but vowed in the presence of the cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, that he would imploy his trauaile and armes, vntill such time as he had done the iustice, that God had appointed him to doo. So that as the pitifull termes of the Request of the said Ladie, had filled the eyes of all the hearers with teares; the Princelie an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere of his Maiestie had quickly dried them with a desire of reuenge. At which time was renued by thē all with a lowd voyce, the oath of not laying downe Armes, vntill such time as they had reuenged the hateful death of the late King their master: &amp; to haue seene their countenances, it had not been for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:190342:5"/>of the League, that this request had been presen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at the day of a Battaile. But the King seeing, that neither shame nor losse could make his enimies come out of <hi>Paris,</hi> and that there was no hope of bringing them to battaile, but by extreame necessitie, hee sent backe againe the Duke <hi>de Longueuile</hi> with the forces that he had brought with him out of <hi>Picardie,</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fresh themselues in the said Prouince, <hi>Monsieur La Nowe</hi> returning with him. Hee did the like also by the Lord <hi>de Giury,</hi> which came and met him with a verie good troupe at his departure from the Suburbs of <hi>Paris,</hi> sending him toward the Countrey of <hi>Brie:</hi> and with the rest which he had, hee was determined to make a little voyage to the Riuer of <hi>Loir,</hi> beeing called thether by manie occasions: and this hee did, staying vntill his strange forces that arose first were further on their way, than they were then. So he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from <hi>Estampes,</hi> on Saturday the x. of Nouem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: and taking his waye through the Countrey of <hi>Beausse,</hi> beeing aduertised that the towne of <hi>Ianuille,</hi> which is in the middest of the same, stopt all the pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sages, desired to winne it in passing. And being arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vppon the Sundare, the Captaine that was in it, made a shewe of defence, but seeing the Canon ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, yeelded it; and departing with 200. harque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buziers, his Maiestie entred the same day, and lodged there the morow after: those of the towne receiuing no displeasure nor discommoditie, no more than if they neuer had reiected the obedience of his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie. The King leauing good garrison in the Castle, which is a reasonable good place, departed thence, going through the Land of <hi>Beausse,</hi> to the towne of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:190342:5"/>
               <hi>Chasteaudun.</hi> Where as soone as hee was arriued, he sent to summon the towne of <hi>Vandesme,</hi> which is his auncient patrimonie, and the auncient title of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decessors; and although that thereby they were dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble his subiects, and therefore the more culpable in taking his enemies part: yet notwithstanding he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a more care to keepe them from further offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, than to punish them for their first fault, did lodge three daies at the said <hi>Chasteaudun,</hi> for to giue them respite to aduise themselues. But God who reserued them for an example of his iustice, would not suffer them to accept the offers which his Maiestie offered them to receiue them to his good fauour: but on the contrarie becomming more insolent and stifnecked, constrained him to assaile them. Whilest the King lodged at <hi>Chasteaudun,</hi> the Captaine of the <hi>Swisses</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued, which were sent by and by after the death of the late King deceased by the Colonells of the foure Regiments, which are in seruice of his Maiestie, for to knowe the pleasure of their superiours, whether they shuld continue in the seruice, or aske their leaue to returne? Who reported vnto his Maiestie, besides the answere which they gaue vnto their said Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels from their superiours, that they had expresse charge from them to giue his Maiestie to vnderstand, that they did not onely command the Colonels and Captaines of the said Regiments to continue in doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him good and faithfull seruice, but also that they did offer him all such other succour as he shuld need; holding from that hower the same alliance and good friendship confirmed with his Maiestie, which they haue had with the Kings his predecessors; which is
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:190342:6"/>a thing quite contrarie to that which his enemies boasted of, that the said Regiments should bee called home, and should doo his Maiestie no seruice. Hee departed from the said <hi>Chasteadun</hi> the fourteenth of Nouember, and the same daye his Armie inuironed the towne of <hi>Vandesme.</hi> The King arriuing at the towne of <hi>Mellay</hi> the sixteenth day, before he lighted, he went and viewed the towne and castle, which are both of reasonable strength, the said towne beeing inclosed with a good ditch well watred, and with a good wall well flanked, and in manie places rampe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red within. The Castle was much stronger, beeing scituated vpon an hill, inuironed with a good ditch towards the field, and a great height ouer the towne, the wall good and defended with manie towers. The gouernor of the place was the Lord <hi>de male-benehard,</hi> who perceiuing that it should be besieged, hee called vnto him certaine Gentlemen his friends, and kept in it an ordinarie garrison of foure Companies of footemen, which were foure hundred men strong, besides those of the town, who were seuen or eight hundred men bearing armes. The day of his arriual he caused the suburbes of the towne to be wonne, &amp; parted my Lordes the Marshalls <hi>de Biron</hi> and <hi>d'Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount,</hi> the one on the one side of the riuer, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on the other side, with the troupes of the saide Armie. And hauing well considered of the forme of the siege, he determined first to deale with the castle, which was of most strength, to make an end at once: for that the Castle being wonne the towne could not escape, which would not so haue happened, if he had begun with the towne. He passed Fridaie and Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daie
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:190342:6"/>to view where he should place the batterie, and to put things in a readines: wherein the presence of his Maiestie, was woorth the labour of fiftie others; for he stird not from the worke all the daye long, and part of the night. In the meane time, the said <hi>Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>benehard</hi> who had before (whilest the King was at <hi>Chasteadun</hi>) desired to parley with the Lord of <hi>Riche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieu</hi> great Prouost of <hi>France,</hi> with whom he was fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarlie acquainted: afterward, when as the saide Prouost did goe to him into the towne, he knew not almost what hee required, but that hee desired, that without yeelding the place, the Armie might retyre. Feeling himselfe afterward pricked in conscience, &amp; in danger of the siege, he required againe to speake with the said Lord of <hi>Richelieu,</hi> who retourning the second time, came backe againe as vncertaine and ill satisfied as at the first. Wherin it well appeared, that God would make him throughlie feele the recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of his deserts, hauing giuen him respite inough long time before the iudgement happened, for to seeke remedie, and not permitted him to helpe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe with resolution, as it came to passe. For his Maiestie hauing passed all the night in condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting and placing the Artillerie in battaile, began at the dawning of the daye to beate two towers of the Castle, to take away the defences of the breach, which hee purposed to make: but after the bestow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of an hundred or an hundred and twentie Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non shot, and hauing made a hole in one of the saide Towers, where onely two men could passe in front, the Souldiers desirous of the assault, certaine of them beeing onely commanded to see if they could lodge
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:190342:7"/>in the said Tower,
<note place="margin">Here the Englishmē wold haue assaulted, and were impeached by Monsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eur Chatti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, and ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>presly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden.</note> they got vp, and with a furie ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the retrenchment: and being followed with the rest, some conducted by the Baron of <hi>Byron,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers by the Lord of <hi>Chastillion,</hi> they made those with in so dismaied, (although they were a great number) that after they presented the combate, they fled; and abandoning the castle ranne into the towne: where they were followed so neerelie, that the said Lordes with part of the said Souldiers, entred pell mell with them, and made themselues within lesse than halfe an howre masters both of the castle &amp; towne. The said <hi>Male-beneherd</hi> and al his Souldiers, being retired into an house, did yeeld themselues incontinent vnto the aforesaid Baron of <hi>Byron,</hi> not otherwise, but at the Kings mercie: so that there was neuer towne seene battered &amp; taken by assault (as it was) with lesse mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; for there was not one man lost of the Armie, &amp; few of his enemies, his said Maiestie hauing pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned all men, except the said <hi>Beneherd,</hi> and a seditious grey Frier, (whom all the inhabitants themselues ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cused to be the author of their mischiefe) were exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted. There was no meane to keep the towne from pillaging, but the Churches his Maiestie caused care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to be preserued, that there entred not one man into them. The morrowe after, hee caused his men of warre to depart the Towne, and suffered the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants to returne to their houses, not permitting them anie longer to be pillaged and ransomed. Hee restored all the Ecclesiasticall persons vnto their seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall charges, much more peaceablie than they were, when the Towne was in occupation of the League. The example of this iustice saued more than a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:190342:7"/>mens liues: for foure or fiue little townes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts, who professed to hold against the King, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king example by <hi>Vandosme,</hi> yeelded themselues in lesse than foure or fiue dayes. The Castle and towne of <hi>Lauerden</hi> began first, and were followed by the Townes of <hi>Mount-ouert, Mount-richard,</hi> and <hi>Chate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>au-du-loyre,</hi> who did all great hurt, especially to <hi>Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> keeping the passages vnto it. The Towne of <hi>Vandosme</hi> beeing taken, finding himselfe so neare <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers,</hi> his Maiestie minded to make a small iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney thether, to see the Lordes of his Councell, and to determine with them certaine principles of his businesse: leauing in the meane while the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie to bee conducted by the Marshall <hi>Byron;</hi> by whose presence hee reduced all the aforesayde Townes, except <hi>Mount richard,</hi> which was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by the voyage which his Maiestie made vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Towers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hee departed from <hi>Meslay</hi> by <hi>Vandosme</hi> vppon Tuesday beeing the one and twentieth of Nouem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and arriued the same day at <hi>Towers,</hi> two ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers within night: where hee was attended with so great ioye and gladnesse of all the people of <hi>Towers,</hi> and such stoare of lights there was in the streates at his arriuall, as if it had been at noone daye.</p>
            <p>The same daye at night, my Lorde the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall of <hi>Vandosme,</hi> came to doo reuerence vnto the King, and receiued intertainment and counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce agreeable to his neerenesse in bloud vnto the Kings Maiestie.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:190342:8"/>
            <p> The morrow after, those of the Parliament, came personally to salute and acknowledge the King; the first President making the Relation: which charge he executed in substance and eloquence most happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and to the great contentment of his Maiestie. All the other bodies of the Chamber of accompts, Court of aides, of the Finances, of the Iustices of the law, and the Maior and Iurats of the Towne did the like. And likewise the Ecclesiasticall persons of the town, all with great shewe of ioye, and hope of happie and quiet Reigne of his said Maiestie: wherin they were the more confirmed by the answeres which they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued likewise from him, in excellent tearmes, and kingly eloquence. The same day the Embassador of <hi>Venice</hi> was graunted audience: where hee presented first of all the letters of the Signiorie vnto his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie, and afterward declared the ioy they had of his happie Succession vnto the Crown; beseeching him to accept the offer of the friendship of the said Signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orie vnto his Maiestie, &amp; to promise and assure them of his, to maintaine the good intercourse betweene his Crowne, and the said Signiorie: whereunto his Maiestie aunswered verie well and wisely. Hee was determined to haue staid but one day at <hi>Towers,</hi> but they were so desirous to see him, that hee could not depart vntill the Saturday following. At which time, with one iourney hee went vnto his Armie at the Castle of <hi>Loyre,</hi> which is ten good leagues off, &amp; and departed thence the morrow after for to goe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>Mans,</hi> which long time hee was desirous to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siege. He lodged twise by the way. And being arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued at <hi>Yuray leuesque</hi> the xxvij. daye, one league di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:190342:8"/>from the said towne of <hi>Mans,</hi> which hee had caused to be inuironed the day before by the Lord of <hi>Fargesse:</hi> he sent to summon the said town. Vnto whom the Lord of <hi>Boisdauphin</hi> (which commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in it for the League) made an answere, as if hee had been resolute to burie himselfe in it, and all those that were with him, rather than to depart out of it; &amp; began to burne a great part of the Suburbes of <hi>La Cousture,</hi> especiallie that part which was without the retrenchment of the said Suburbes. But the said Lord of Fargesse came vpon them with his troupe, and sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued a great part of the aforenamed Suburbes. Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after the Baron <hi>Byron,</hi> and <hi>Chastilion</hi> arriued with the greatest part of the French Infanterie, by whome the same night was the aforesaid retrench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment wonne, which was in some places twentie foote high, and might easelie haue attended the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non: and from that time it was supposed, that they were easier to be dealt with, than was looked for. The morrow after the xxviij. of the said moneth of Nouember, his Maiestie came and lodged in the said Suburbes, which is faire, and in a maneer more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious to lodge in, than the Towne. And the same daye hee caused all the other Suburbes to be wonne, except the Suburbes of <hi>Saint Iohn,</hi> that was on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther side of the Riuer of <hi>Sarthe,</hi> which was wonne the morrow after, the said <hi>Boysdauphin</hi> hauing cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed more than halfe to bee burned, and that which was next the bridge, which was the fairest housing. All their valour appeared in nothing but in that. For three daies folowing, whilst the Gabeons wer a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and other preparatiues necessarie for the batte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:190342:9"/>and the pieces brought to their places, his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie himselfe hauing passed whole nights therein, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the second day of September, began to beat cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine defences of the wall of the said Towne. Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatelie after the first vollies of the Cannon, that braue speach which they had giuen at the summon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Towne, was turned quite contrarie into submission. So that <hi>Boisdauphin</hi> and his people not i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magining that they should haue been so sharplie delt withall (for within three houres they shoulde haue had assault giuen them, which they were not wel re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solued to abide) demaunded a Parley; and in fine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore two of the clocke in the afternoone, the saide Towne was yeelded vnto his Maiestie: notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that there were in it more than an hundred gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, and twentie ensignes of footemen, who du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the time of the Parley, did dishonour each other publiquely. The Gentlemen said, that the Souldiers would not fight, and the Souldiers said, that agaynst their wills the Gentlemen would compound. As in truth it was a thing verie strange, hauing caused the people to spend more than 5000. crownes in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tefying of the Suburbs of their Townes, burnt more than a 100000. crownes worth of housing, and (as it is said) ruined the Countrey six times as much more, for to abide three vollyes of the Cannon, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to yeeld the Towne: which without the great care that his Maiestie had had of it, had neuer beene kept from pillage: but hee commaunded the gates to be kept shut. And to the intent that none should take occasion to go into it, he would not lodge in it him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, but kept in the suburbes where he first was lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:190342:9"/>There were two soldiers found with a Chalice which they had stollen, and were hanged immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately, although they were knowen to be men of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue. The thundring of the Cannon was heard at <hi>Le Fort-berne-herd,</hi> when the Counte <hi>Brisaac</hi> was arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with two Regiments to succour the said Town of <hi>Mans:</hi> who was so made afraid, that he ran back againe 12 leagues; and in retiring, fell by chance into the Reisters quarter that serued his Maiestie, who would not dislodge as they were appointed, &amp; carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away for their bootie 30. or 40. horse and chariots without the losse of anie man. His Maiestie restored first into the towne of <hi>Mans,</hi> the Bishop and the Lord of <hi>Fargesse</hi> his brother, which had been Gouernour before, &amp; pardoned the rest of the inhabitants, who came all, aswell Ecclesiasticall, as other, to giue him thankes, with protestation of their fidelitie and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect obedience. During the aboad, which the King made at <hi>Mans,</hi> fiue daies after the taking of it, the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle of <hi>Beaumont</hi> yeelded first of all, and the Castle of <hi>Touvoie,</hi> and likewise the greatest part of the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, which were in the Towne of <hi>Mans,</hi> and others which had been seduced by the League, &amp; put them selues into the Kings seruice; who was accompanied in that siege with more than fiue hundred Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the Prouinces thereabout. Amongst whom there were manie Marquesses, Counties, and other great Lords.</p>
            <p>At that time the Townes of <hi>Sablee, Lauall, Chaste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>augountere,</hi> which are all Townes of importance, and manie others which are not of so great name, were reduced vnto the King.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:190342:10"/>
            <p> Before his departure from <hi>Mans,</hi> his Maiestie was determined to take the Towne and Castle of <hi>Alan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son:</hi> and whilest his Armie marched thether, vnder the conduct of the Lord Marshall <hi>Byron,</hi> and of the Lord Baron <hi>Byron</hi> his sonne Marshall of the Campe, he thought good to make a small voyage to <hi>Lauall,</hi> to the intent, by his presence to comfort the Nobilitie and people of the Countrey, which were newly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced vnto his obedience, and likewise to cause the Prince <hi>Dumbees</hi> to come thether whom his Maiestie desired to see.</p>
            <p>He arriued at the said <hi>Lauall</hi> the ix. day of Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and there came and met him a great way with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Towne, all the Ecclesiasticall persons, aswell Chanons, as other religious persons, with their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments, as they were accustomed to goe in Proces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion: and hauing by the mouth of one of them made their submission, and protestation of their fidelitie and obedience, accompanied the King vntill he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred the Towne, singing alwaies <hi>Viue le Roy,</hi> in verie good musicke. There came out likewise the Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates of the Towne, and met him: and the people cried each where with an incessaunt crye, <hi>Viue le Roy,</hi> whilest that his Maiestie passed thorough the Towne.</p>
            <p>He abode there eight or tenne dayes, and the afore sayd Prince <hi>Dumbees</hi> arriued with a great Companie of the Nobilitie of <hi>Britaine,</hi> to whome it was great honour to be knowen vnto his Maiestie, and he was most courteously receiued.</p>
            <p>Certaine of his Troupe departing from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, tooke in their waye comming the Castle of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:190342:10"/>
               <hi>Chasteubriant,</hi> and brought with them the Captaine and manie others prisoners.</p>
            <p>His Maiestie hauing spent certaine dayes with the Prince <hi>Dumbees,</hi> and taking order for the affaires of that Prouince, he sent him againe to his charge; and dispatched <hi>Mounsieur</hi> Marshall <hi>D'aumount,</hi> for to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his strange Forces together. And the King came from <hi>Lauall</hi> vnto the Towne of <hi>Maienna-la-Iahes,</hi> where he was verie well receiued, and assured him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe of the Castle, without leauing anie other Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rison in the Towue. Hee arriued at <hi>Alanson</hi> the three and twentieth daye, hauing passed a most foule Countrey.</p>
            <p>And as concerning my Lord Marshall <hi>Byron,</hi> who departed with the Armie from the Towne of <hi>Mans</hi> the ninth day of the said moneth of December, hee could not arriue at <hi>Alanson</hi> till the fifteenth daye fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, by reason of the foule waie,
<note place="margin">Here the English en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred a bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warke or rauelin, wel inuironed and defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with water, by pulling downe a draw bridg with a hooke, and wold haue assaied to to enter the towne, but them arshal Byron for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bad them expreslie.</note> which hindred the carriage of the Ordinaunce: and hauing caused the Towne to be inuironed certaine dayes before by the Lord of <hi>Artray,</hi> who at his first comming tooke the Suburbes, and droue them of the Towne after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to come to composition, and yeeld; Captaine <hi>Lago</hi> (which was Gouernour) retiring himselfe into the Castle with foure hundred and fiftie Souldiers, making shewe that he would defend it; the place be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing verie good and strong, inuironed with water, good walls, good flankes, and great Towers.</p>
            <p>The saide Lord Marshall beeing entered into the Towne, kept so good order in it, that it was not seen that it had been besieged, the shops beeing kept open the same daye, as if it had been in peace.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:190342:11"/>
            <p> At the hower of the entrie, he caused the artillerie to be brought before the Castle, and shot at the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, and had so farre proceeded in this businesse, that hauing found meanes to take away their water, he could in little space haue made breach. His Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie being arriued as aforesaid, he shewed him all that was done, and also what was intended to bee done: who answered immediatelie that the siege wold not be long,</p>
            <p>The said Captaine <hi>Lago</hi> that was in the Castle did imagine little lesse, and at the summons which his Maiestie did cause to be made, for to declare that hee was come, he began to be astonied: and the morrow after he parleyed, and the same day the composition was agreed vppon, to saue his life and his souldiers, with their armes and baggage.</p>
            <p>His Maiestie hauing foreseene for the assuraunce of the said place, left for Gouernor the Lord <hi>Artray,</hi> with a good garrison in the Towne and Castle, and departing the seuen and twentieth daye, he went and lodged at <hi>Seas,</hi> where the Bishop and Cleargie with the Maiestrates came and met him, and receiued him so well, that hee trusted vnto the inhabitants of the place, without leauing therein anie other Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son.</p>
            <p>He departed thence the morrow after for to go to <hi>Argenton,</hi> which is a good Towne, in which there is a Castle of reasonable strength: and there was in the said Towne and Castle three Ensignes of foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, which the Countie of <hi>Brisaac</hi> had lefte there: who with the <hi>Cheualier Picard</hi> and his Regiment were come from <hi>Paris,</hi> and had promised to shew
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:190342:11"/>himselfe at all the sieges which his Maiestie woulde take in hand, and impeach him from the taking of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of the Townes in the Countrey of <hi>Maine,</hi> and base <hi>Normandie:</hi> notwithstanding hee shewed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe at none.</p>
            <p>Those of the Towne of <hi>Argenton,</hi> being determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to yeeld vnto his Maiestie, came &amp; met him, most humbly beseeching him to receiue them into his fauonr, which he graunted them most willingly; which the Souldiers seeing, retired themselues into the Castle; beseeching his Maiestie to suffer them to depart with their liues &amp; baggage, which he consen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto.</p>
            <p>His maiestie was aduertised the same day, that those of the Garrison of the Castle of <hi>Damfront,</hi> vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that he had summoned the Inhabitants of the Towne, and that they were determined to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the King, entered into consultation what they should doo, being of contrarie opinions, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon put themselues in Armes one against another: It hapned, that those that would submit themselues to his Maiestie although they were not halfe so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie in number as as the others were, encouraged with the Iustice of their cause, had the Victorie: and the Baron of <hi>Vernie</hi> gouernour of the said Castle was slaine, and certeine other: whereupon aswell those of the Castle as those of the Towne sent vnto the King to craue his fauour and clemencie, which they obteined. And he sent vnto the Towne to bee assured of both parties, which was done, without o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting anie force or excesse.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:190342:12"/>
            <p> The King remaining for this cause one whole day at <hi>Argenton,</hi> departed thence vpon Sundaye the one and thirtieth of December, for to goe to the siege of <hi>Falese,</hi> the Castle whereof is verie strong, &amp; estee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be the best place in base <hi>Normandie,</hi> next vnto the Castle of <hi>Caen,</hi> and therefore the Counte of <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sac</hi> put himselfe into it, with the <hi>Cheualier Picard</hi> and his Regiment, hauing wonne vnto them manie Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen and Souldiers of the Countrey, vaunting that they would repay the honour of their companions, who had yeelded and lost all the other Townes, and that at this place, all the spoyles that had been gotten, should be surrendred.</p>
            <p>His Maiestie the night before, had sent the Baron of <hi>Byron</hi> to inuiron it, with certaine Troupes of men of warre, aswell foote as horse, who came thether so happely, that he found the Conte of <hi>Brisac</hi> come out of the Towne, purposing to burne the Towne of <hi>Guibray,</hi> which is as it were one of the Suburbes of <hi>Faleze.</hi> Who perceiuing the said Troupes, the fier he brought with him was not anye waye able to heate him so much as to make him abide them, but returning with all speede into the Towne, hee lefte <hi>Guibray</hi> whole: and the said Baron <hi>de Byron</hi> did not onely ceaze vpon it to lodge his Maiestie, but also at the same instant did make them runne away out of the Suburbes of the Towne, ioyning euen to the gate, part whereof they themselues had burned a litle before.</p>
            <p>His Maiestie beeing arriued, went presently with the Mareshall of <hi>Byron</hi> to viewe the Towne and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle, which are both strong; the said Towne beeing
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:190342:12"/>inuironed with a great poole, whose water could not be drawen away, the wall being good, and flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with good towers, and the approaches difficile for the planting of Ordinaunce; the Castle beeing much stronger, garnished with great and strong to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers and verie good wals, with a donion seperated, ditched with good and great ditches: and besides all this the Counte of <hi>Brisac</hi> well accompanied with Gentlemen, Captaines and Souldiers, with a great showe that hee would not haue made this proofe but with intent to get honour, and to defend the place ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuallie, as in deede vnto the Summons which his Maiestie did make the next day, he made an answere conuenient vnto such a resolution, which was that he had vowed vnto God, that he would neuer speak of anie composition for that Towne, which made all men thinke, that he would haue defended it bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than he did.</p>
            <p>His Maiestie (whose presence in such like affaires is the perfect schoole of extreame diligence, determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned so to begin, as that he would not make 2. workes of one) did batter the Castle; for that the Castle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wonne, the Towne could not hold out, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed the morrowe after, with great expedition, Gabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to be made for the batterie, bags to be filled with earth, and all things necessarie to be done. Which was so diligently followed, that in lesse than three dayes all was in a readinesse, and had begun to batter vpon the Thursday, but that he stayed for three Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons which <hi>Mounsieur Montpensier</hi> brought him out of the Castle of <hi>Caen:</hi> which could not arriue at the said siege vntill that verie day.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:190342:13"/>
            <p> With the Duke <hi>Montpensier</hi> there came betwixt twelue and fifteene hundred French Souldiers, and a good Troupe of the Gentlemen of the Countrey, &amp; certaine Companies of men of Armes. Those with in the Towne did neuer sallye out: but otherwise made alwaies a good shewe of a resolution in them, and in their words were ouer lauish, performing af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward so little as they did.</p>
            <p>His Maiestie pretending to make three batteries, two of which, from sundrie parts should batter at the breach of the said Castle; and the third to bee placed vpon a Rocke, which should scoure curtaine wise a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, behinde the breach of the said Castle. Hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan vpon Friday the fifth day of Ianuarie at eight of the clocke to beate two great towers, which flanked from the one vnto the other; the one of which ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued for a defence vnto the breach, which he purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to make. After the bestowing of foure hundred Cannon shot, the top of one of the Towers beeing fallen, and a hole being made in the other tower that defended the breache, which hole opened into the said Castle, his Maiestie caused it to be battered for the speedie breach which would be made in it: for there needed but the beating away of a little piece of the wall. Then he commaunded certaine Troupes of Souldiers, to goe and viewe if they could lodge in the said Tower, vpon which certain of them en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring the hole, which was pierced through the To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer into the Castle, finding no resistance, called their companions, and so entring one after another, in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie short space they became Masters both of Castle and Towne.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:190342:13"/>
            <p> Those within being sore dismaied, without anie fight they retired them selues into the Donion spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of before; out of which they sent three Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men the same daye, to beseech the King to receaue them vpon anie composition; who aunswered, that he would not receane them, but at his own pleasure; and that they should prooue his clemencie, without binding himselfe vnto anie condition. Yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, the morrowe after suffering the Countie <hi>Brisac</hi> to come and submit himselfe vnto him, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ouercome with the pitie he had vpon the young Gentleman, graunted to chuse fifteene of the best of them, whom he would keepe prisoners as warlike e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, and the rest should be at his Maiesties dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition.</p>
            <p>It were not well done to take away the Souldiers honour that were at this siege, who in truth did their indeuour: but wee must acknowledge this to haue been Gods worke, as a thing most admirable vnto vs that saw it, that at one instant those that seemed to be furious Lions, were metamorphosid into meeker things than Lambes. The Towne being thus taken by assault, could not be preserued from pillaging and saccaging: so that by this may comparison be made, between the intertainment that those receiue, which flie vnto his Maiesties clemencie, and those which obstinately attend the force of his Armie; the one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made whollie desolate, and the other reioycing in a full and perfect quietnes, making a profit of their losse, obtaining by their taking and reduction free li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, in stead of the hard captiuitie which they suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered vnder the vnlawfull gouernment of others.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:190342:14"/>
            <p> It is to be well considered, of what great value the wise and happie gouernement of his Maiestie hath been; his enemies being constrained to confesse, that it is to be wondered at, and vntill this time vnknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, hauing in lesse than two moneths trauailed eight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>score leagues, with such a great Armie as his, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with a great deale of Ordinaunce, manie <hi>Swit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zers,</hi> and other strange Nations; and in this time ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Suburbes of <hi>Paris,</hi> made fiue or sixe nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble sieges, taken fourteene or fifteene notable towns, hauing eleared the Prouinces of <hi>Vandesme, Tourain, Aniou,</hi> and <hi>Maine,</hi> of all that his enemies helde: and not onelie recouered the Townes, but the hearts and affections of those that most hated him. All his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploites being done by the force of his armes, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, and terror of the same; without practises of treasons, murders, monopoles, or fraudes: leauing those guiles, vnto those that deale with vniust acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, assuring himselfe his cause to bee so iust, that it was able to support it selfe without the helpe of anie thing of a contrarie nature, hauing alwaies this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable maxime in regard, that euil can neuer serue to anie good purpose.</p>
            <p>Is it possible that GOD hath so condemned the poore inhabitants of Towns, that he wil suffer them anie longer to be so blinded in spirit and bodie, as not to consider of the mischiefes wherin they haue plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged themselues, and howe those vnto whome they giue themselues ouer, and receiue for friendes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come immediatelie the cruellest enemies they can haue: who after they haue sucked from them al that they can drawe, while they are with them, and by
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:190342:14"/>little and little made them subiects to the simplest sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers of their troupes, if there bee anie brute of the Kings Armie comming, in stead of preparing to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue the people, vse no other industrie, but to burne halfe their Townes, and the greatest part of the Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages within two miles round about, then making them to trauaile daye and night in making rampiers and retrenchments: and yet when they are besieged, if they doo but see the Cannon, thinke themselues excused of their honour, in making their compositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to depart with their liues and baggage saued; lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing no token behinde them of their protection, but one halfe of the Townes in ashes, &amp; the people with a halter about their neckes: so that if the Prince they haue to deale with were not mercifull, a whole for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest could not furnish for gallowes that would be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed.</p>
            <p>Is it possible that they see not nor know not (that those which haue beene so readie to mooue vp these seditions, are now so audacious &amp; malicious as to maintaine them? and that his Maiestie defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his kingdome against tyrannie, his people against strangers, and iustice against iniquitie) the successe of his enterprises, must needes be correspondent to the equitie of his cause; that ineuitable destruction will come vpon them that resist him, if the word of God (as it is) be true. For our parts, we most humblie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech God, to make them able to consider and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge it, and aboue all things, that it woulde please God to preserue his Maiestie, from al mishaps that might happen vnto his person, and prolong his life: for so great need haue we of <hi>France</hi> of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:190342:15"/>that the ordinarie course of the longest liuers would be but too short.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AFter the siege of</hi> Falese, <hi>the King gaue the English men leaue to depart; and he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe with his Armie, to weete, the French men and Switzers, Rutters &amp; Lants-knights went vnto</hi> Lizeux, <hi>which within ten dayes after he tooke: and from thence his Maiestie went vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> Humflet, <hi>which he did batter vpon Fridaie the xvi. of Ianuarie. At which time, part of our English Forces were shipped at</hi> Dines <hi>in</hi> Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandie, <hi>and the rest, the morrow after.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:190342:15"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>